Guide to the Fred M. Shideler Papers 1940-1983
Oregon State University Archives
Fred M. Shideler Papers
1940-1983
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
Consult repository.
Shideler, Fred Merle.
1.3 cubic feet
The Shideler Papers document the OSU presidency of James H. Jensen through materials created and assembled by Fred Shideler in his role as head of information services for the University.
Biographical Note:
Shideler was born in Girard, Kansas, in 1904. He earned a bachelor's degree in journalism from Kansas State College in 1927 and an MA in education from Oregon State College in 1941. In 1929, he began his career at OSU, one that spanned 41 years, as a journalism instructor and an assistant in the OSC News Bureau.
Shideler was promoted to assistant professor and journalism department head in 1932; to associate professor in 1939; and to professor in 1944. From January through March 1944 he worked in the Office of War Information in Washington, D.C., and from April 1944 through September 1945 he was the information assistant for the OSC Extension Service's Emergency Farm Labor Service. During that time he took over 200 photographs of the farm labor program's activities throughout the state. He returned to teaching journalism in the fall of 1945.
In 1952 he became head of information services; in 1967 he was appointed director of university relations. Shideler also served as administrative assistant to Oregon governors Paul L. Patterson and Elmo Smith in 1956. Shideler retired from OSU in 1970. He died in Corvallis on May 11, 1993.
Most of the collection consists of drafts of speeches, statements, news releases, and correspondence written by Shideler for President James H. Jensen, 1961-1969. This series also includes a photocopy of a scrapbook compiled to document the recognition dinner given for Jensen at the time of his retirement in 1969.
The remainder of the collection consists of subject files. These include a typescript of a biography of President William Jasper Kerr, by Edwin T. Reed; materials pertaining to the retirement of E. B. Lemon and President A. L. Strand; records of an oral history project documenting the career of Strand; materials pertaining to the University's Centennial in 1968; a student paper written by Shideler in 1940; papers presented at annual meetings of the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges in 1962 and 1970; and photographs of James H. Jensen.
The Fred M. Shideler Papers are organized into eight series. Most series are arranged chronologically.
Dept. of Information Records (RG 10); Journalism Dept. Records (RG 91); Extension Service Records (RG 111); News and Communication Services Records (RG 203); Agricultural Communications Photograph Collection (P 120); MC - Shideler, Fred.
Jensen, James H.; Kerr, William Jasper, 1863-1947.; Lemon, E. B. (Erwin Bertran), 1889-1979.; Strand, A. L., (August Leroy), 1894-; Reed, Edwin Thomas, 1872-1948.
Oregon State University--Anniversaries, etc.; Oregon State University--Centennial, celebrations, etc.
Universities and colleges--Public relations--Oregon--Corvallis.; College administrators--Oregon--Corvallis.; College presidents--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
Oregon; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Colleges and Universities; Journalism
- William Jasper Kerr Biography, by Edwin T. Reed, ca. 1948; Series I
  - Illustrations (Box 1)
  - Final draft of text (483 typescript pages) (Box 1)
- Trends in Teaching Journalism in High School, student paper, 1940; Series II (Box 1)
- E.B. Lemon Retirement, 1959; Series III
  - Oregon Stater article (Box 1)
  - Recognition dinner (Box 1)
- A.L. Strand, 1953-1983; Series IV
  - Dinner and recognition, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Obituary, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Strand Lectureship (First Presbyterian Church), 1982 (Box 1)
  - OSU Building Names Committee, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Strand Oral History Project
    - Leman/Shideler memos, 1981 (Box 1)
    - Reminiscences, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
    - A.L. Strand documents (copies), 1953-1964 (Box 1)
    - Oral interview questions and tips (Box 1)
    - Oregon Committee for the Humanities grant proposals, 1981 (Box 1)
    - List of potential interviewees (Box 1)
- National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges, Annual Meetings, 1962-1970; Series V
  - November 1962, Washington, D.C.
    - Paper presented by Shideler, "How Can We Best Tell the Land-Grant Idea of Educational Services?" (Box 1)
  - November 1970, Washington, D.C.
    - Public Information program (Box 1)
    - Panel discussion remarks presented by Shideler (Box 1)
- OSU Centennial, 1968; Series VI
  - Newspaper articles (Box 1)
  - News releases (Box 1)
  - Charter Day activities (Box 1)
  - Documentary film text (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous, 1961-1983; Series VII
  - Oregonians Against Measure #9 (property tax elimination measure), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Oregon State Employees Association (OSEA), 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, clippings, writings, etc., 1961-1983 (Box 1)
- James H. Jensen, 1960-1969; Series VIII
  - Biographical information (Box 2)
  - New President Search, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Jensen Home (Box 2)
  - Speeches, letters, etc. drafted by Shideler for Jensen
    - Miscellaneous statements, news releases and correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 2)
    - City Club of Portland Speech, March 13, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Speeches and background information, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous statements, news releases and correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 3)
    - Speeches, 1965-1967 (Box 3)
    - 1965-66 Report of the President (Box 3)
    - University of Oregon Medical School, June 3, 1966 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous statements, news releases and correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - National Assn. of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges annual meeting, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous statements, news releases and correspondence, etc., 1968 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Day Talks, 1963-1968 (Box 4)
    - Commencement speeches, 1965-1969 (Box 4)
    - Resignation, 1969 (Box 4)
  - James H. Jensen Recognition Dinner scrapbook (photocopy), 1969 (Box 4)
- Photographs, 1961-1969; Series IX
  - Shideler and OSU president James H. Jensen with OSU alumni from the Long Beach (CA) area, ca. 1964. (Box 5)
  - James H. Jensen, visit to campus prior to selection as president, 1961 (Box 5)
  - James H. Jensen, portraits, ca. 1961 (Box 5)
  - James H. Jensen speaking at the recognition dinner for F.E. Price (Box 5)
  - Mixer in the Memorial Union Lounge prior to Jensen Recognition Dinner, June 1969 (Box 5)
  - Roy and Marilyn Young, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Award plaque presented to Jensen at Commencement, June 1969 (Box 5)
  - Commencement crowd in Memorial Union Quad, June 1969 (Box 5)
  - unidentified (Box 5)